A Guide to the Papers of Admiral John Randolph Tucker 1865-1897
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Admiral John Randolph Tucker 1865-1897
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 40
One Hollinger document Case.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Commander Douglas Tucker, USN, January 8, 1980
Biographical/Historical Information
John Randolph Tucker was born January 31, 1812 in Alexandria, Virginia. His parents were John Tucker, originally from Bermuda, and Sara Douglas, daughter of Dr. Charles Douglas, a physician who came to America after the Revolution. The Tucker family, some of whom had been in Virginia since before the Revolution, produced a number of prominent men in Virginia's political and social life.
After attending private schools in Alexandria, Tucker entered the U.S. Navy as a midshipman on June 1, 1826. Although six years later he passed the examination for advancement, there were no vacancies at that time and he had to wait until December 20, 1837 to be promoted to Lieutenant. As Lieutenant Commander he commanded the Stromboli during the Mexican War. Tucker received his commission as Commander on September 14, 1855 when he took over the command of the Pennsylvania. His last duty in the U.S. Navy was as Ordnance Officer of the Norfolk Navy Yard, from which he resigned due to the secession of Virginia.
Tucker was appointed Commander, first of the Virginia Navy and then the Confederate States Navy, at which time he assumed command of the Patrick Henry, formerly a U.S. Navy Steamer which was seized and converted into a Confederate man-of-war. As commander of the Patrick Henry, Tucker participated in battles with the Union Navy at Hampton Roads and Drewry's Bluff. In August of 1862, Tucker took over command of the Chicora at Charleston, South Carolina. Following Tucker's surrender in April 1865 at the Battle of Saylor's Creek, he was sent North as a prisoner of war. After his release July 24, 1865, he returned to the South to work as an agent of the Southern Express Company of Raleigh, North Carolina.
While Tucker was in Raleigh, the Peruvian Minister to the United States contacted him to arrange an interview in Washington. Peru, which was at war with Spain, invited Tucker to join their Navy as a Rear Admiral, bringing with him two staff officers. Tucker accepted and went to Peru with Captain David Porter McCorkle and Commander Walter Raleigh Butt. Although some Peruvian Naval Officers objected to a foreigner in command of their fleet, Tucker distinguished himself in battle with Spain.
Following his resignation in 1871 from the Peruvian Navy, Tucker was appointed President of the Peruvian Hydrographical Commission of the Amazon. This Commission, which explored and surveyed the Upper Amazon River and its tributaries, discovered two new rivers, the Trinidad and the Herrera- yacu. Upon completion of the expedition, Tucker traveled to New York to meet with engravers to make maps and atlases from the Commission's findings.
Tucker retired to Petersburg, Virginia, until his sudden death on June 12, 1883. He was buried in Norfolk next to his wife, the former Virginia Webb, whom he married June 7, 1838, and who died in 1858. Their children were Randolph Tucker, Tarleton Webb Tucker, and Virginius Tucker.
Scope and Content Information
The John Randolph Tucker papers, many of which are in Spanish, deal primarily with his service as President of the Peruvian Hydrographical Commission of the Amazon. They are divided into four series: Correspondence, Legal and Business Papers, Publications and Newspaper Clippings, and Miscellaneous. Of these, Series I: Correspondence is by far the most extensive and important. The letters describe the expedition of the steamer Tambo and the difficulties encountered by Tucker and the Commission. These include hostile natives, as well as financial and other problems in their dealings with the Peruvian government. Correspondence from Captain James H. Rochelle, Tucker's friend and a Commission member, indicates that for years afterward Tucker and Rochelle suffered from malaria contracted on the expedition. Letters in Subseries C written by Tucker's son and Rochelle's nephew reveal that as late as 1897, years after the deaths of Tucker and Rochelle, the Peruvian government still had not paid the Commission members the money owed them.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Admiral John R. Tucker
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: 1870 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: 1871 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: 1872-1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: 1874 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: 1877-1880 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker: undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1865-1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1867 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1868-1869 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1870 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1871 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1872 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1873 (Box-folder Folder 13)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1874 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): 1880 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Admiral John R. Tucker (incoming): undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries B: Captain James H. Rochelle
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: 1872 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: 1873-1874 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: January-April 1876 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: June-December 1876 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: January-April 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: May-December 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle: 1878-1882 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Captain James H. Rochelle (incoming): 1865, 1878 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Subseries C: John Randolph Tucker
    - John Randolph Tucker (incoming): 1897 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 26)
    - John Randolph Tucker (incoming): 1895-1896 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Subseries D: Other correspondence
    - Other (copy): 1794 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Other (copy): 1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Other: 1873-1874 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Other: 1897 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Other: undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series II: Legal and Business Papers
  - Registro metereologico by F. L. Galt March-June 1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Contract between Admiral J. R. Tucker and Pusey, Jones and Company: October 13, 1869 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Passport for Admiral J. R. Tucker: December 17, 1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Certificate for services rendered on the Mario, issued to Admiral J. R. Tucker: May 12, 1874 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Receipt - land purchased by Admiral J. R. Tucker October 3, 1870 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Receipts for Admiral J. R. Tucker: 1874, 1879 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series III: Publications and Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper Clippings (English): 1864-1865 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Spanish): 1868-1872 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Brief for the Defense 1869 (Box-folder Box 1, folder 41)
  - Congressional Materials: 1878 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Advertisements for Forthcoming Books: 1870's (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous
  - Calling cards: undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Unattached envelopes: 1880's (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Other: undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 46)